Guide to the Yale Collection of American Literature Reading Series
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Yale Collection of American Literature reading series
2002-2006
YCAL MSS 211
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
3.68
(6 boxes)
Sound recordings on compact discs, audio cassettes, fliers, pamphlets and broadsides documenting the Yale Collection of American Literature Reading Series. The collection includes recordings and printed material generated by annual Yale student poetry readings; a videocassette and printed material related to the Bollingen Prize Readings at Center Church in September 2002; and recordings and publicity materials for readings by established and published contemporary American poets from 2002 to 2006. New readings are added to the collection annually, documenting the Yale Collection of American Literature's ongoing speaker series.
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library. Collection of American Literature
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of the Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library, 2005-2010.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Boxes 3, 5-6 (original recordings): Restricted fragile material. Digital Reference copies available. Consult Access Services for further information.
Existence and Location of Copies
Digital reference copies of recordings are available and have been provided in the main box sequence.
Yale Collection of American Literature Reading Series
Yale Collection of American Literature Reading Series events have been recorded since the fall of 2002. The Collection generally hosts three readings an academic term; each spring the series includes the annual Yale Student Poets reading, including both graduate and undergraduate student poets. For more information contact the series curator, Nancy Kuhl, at nancy.kuhl@yale.edu.
Scope and Contents
The Yale Collection of American Literature Reading Series consists of recordings of poetry readings sponsored by the Yale Collection of American Literature as well as fliers, announcements, pamphlets and broadsides produced to publicize and accompany the series. The collection includes recordings of annual Yale student poetry readings, as well as readings by established and published contemporary American poets. Recordings and printed material related to the Bollingen Prize Readings in September 2002 are also present. The finding aid will be updated as new readings are recorded as part of the Yale Collection of American Literature's ongoing speaker series.
Poets represented in this collection include Elizabeth Alexander, Sherman Alexie, John Ashbery, Robert Creeley, Kwame Dawes, Rita Dove, Debra Magpie Earling, Forrest Gander, Peter Gizzi, Louise Gluck, Jorie Graham, Matthea Harvey, Terence Hayes, William Heyen, Fanny Howe, LeAnne Howe, Susan Howe, Major Jackson, Alan Jenkins, Allison Joseph, Ann Lauterbach, Marijane Meaker, Marilyn Nelson, Ron Padgett, Michael Palmer, Claudia Rankine, Adrienne Rich, Lisa Steinman, Arthur Sze, Cole Swensen, Rodrigo Toscano, Natasha Trethewey, Elizabeth Willis, and C. D. Wright.
American poetry -- 21st century; Oral interpretation of poetry; Poets, American -- 21st century; Sound recordings; Poets -- 21st century; Alexander, Elizabeth, 1962-; Alexie, Sherman, 1966-; Allen, Austin, 1984-; Baumgartner, Alice, 1987-; Bernstein, Charles, 1950-; Bidart, Frank, 1939-; Bök, Christian, 1966-; Brady, Paula, 1984-; Breit, Jonathan Pollack, 1984-; Creeley, Robert, 1926-2005; Dawes, Kwame Senu Neville, 1962-; Deutsch, Abigail, 1984-; Dixon, Nicole, 1982-; Dove, Rita, 1952-; Drew, Rose; Drury, Annmarie; Earling, Debra Magpie, 1957-; Farago, Jason; Foster, Brett; Foust, Graham W., 1970-; Gander, Forrest, 1956-; Garcia, Edgar, 1983-; Givens, Rebecca; Gizzi, Peter, 1959-; Glück, Louise, 1943-; Gorin, David, 1982-; Graham, Jorie, 1950-; Harvey, Matthea, 1973-; Heyen, William, 1940-; Howe, LeAnne; Howe, Susan, 1937-; Idehen, Valerie; Komunyakaa, Yusef, 1947-; Jenkins, Alan, 1955-; Joseph, Allison, 1967-; Kopley, Emily, 1984-; Lauterbach, Ann, 1942-; Lee, Amy, 1988-; Malech, Dora; Marris, Laura, 1987-; Meaker, Marijane, 1927-; Mitchell, Caitlin, 1983-; Nelson, Marilyn, 1946-; Nemser, Alexander, 1983-; Oh, Rosanna, 1988-; Palmer, Michael, 1943-; Phillips, Helen Coleman, 1981-; Pugh, Megan, 1982-; Rankine, Claudia, 1963-; Rich, Adrienne, 1929-2012; Robinson, Elizabeth, 1961-; Rockwood, Catherine; Sider, Justin, 1982-; Sorkin, Jenni; Sorkin, Mara; Steinman, Lisa Malinowski, 1950-; Stone, Sarah M. (Sarah Margaret), 1978-; Swensen, Cole, 1955-; Sze, Arthur; Toscano, Rodrigo; Waldman, Kate, 1987-; Wang, Ivy Y., 1984-; Ward, Eric, 1987-; Willis, Elizabeth; Wright, C. D., 1949-2016; Yi, Ivanna, 1983-; Zuckerman, Jeffrey, 1987-; Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library. Collection of American Literature; Yale University -- Students
- Audio Recordings of YCAL Readings, 2002-2010; Series I; 0.42; (1 box)
  Scope and Contents
  Series I, Audio Recordings of YCAL Readings, is arranged chronologically by date of reading. Digital reference copies for each reading are available.
  - The Bollingen Prize Readings at Center Church (2 discs), 2002 September (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Readings by Bollingen Prize winners: John Ashbery, Robert Creeley, Louise Gluck, John Hollander, Donald Justice, Stanley Kunitz, W. S. Merwin, Gary Snyder, Mark Strand, and Richard Wilbur
  - Howe, Susan. Poetry reading, 2002 November 13 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Lauterbach, Ann. Poetry reading, 2002 December 5 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Howe, LeAnne. Reading, 2003 February 20 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Jenkins, Alan. Poetry reading, 2003 March 26 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Yale Student Poets. Poetry reading, 2003 April 23 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Students: rose drew, Jason Farago Brett Foster, Rebecca Givens, David Gorin, Dora Malech, and Catherine Rockwood
  - Yale Collegium Musicum. "Mina, Maxine, Marianne... and More: new settings by Yale composers of texts by women whose papers are held in the Beinecke Library: H.D., Maxine Kumin, Mina Loy, Marianne Moore, and Gertrude Stein.", 2003 October 1 (Box 1, Folder 6a)
    Performed by The Yale Collegium Musicum with special guest Maxine Kumin
  - Graham, Jorie. Poetry reading, 2003 October 21 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Creeley, Robert. Poetry reading, 2003 November 13 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Gander, Forrest and C. D. Wright. Poetry reading, 2004 February 3 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Meaker, Marijane. Poetry reading, 2004 March 23 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Steinman, Lisa Malinowski. Poetry reading, 2004 April 13 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Yale Student Poets. Poetry reading, 2004 April 20 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Students: Jonathan Breit, Abigail Deutsch, Nicole Dixon, Annmarie Drury, David Gorin, Valerie Idehen, Emily Kopley, Alexander Nemser, Helen Phillips, Megan Pugh
  - Gluck, Louise. Poetry reading, 2004 April 26 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Rich, Adrienne Cecile. Poetry reading, 2004 September 30 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Heyen, William. Poetry reading, 2004 October 13 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Palmer, Michael. Poetry reading, 2004 November 10; 1 (Box 3, Item barcode 39002099364870)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Audiovisual material. Restricted fragile. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
  - Dove, Rita. Poetry reading, Battel Chapel, 2004 November 30; 1 (Box 3, Item barcode 39002099364888)
  - Sze, Arthur. Poetry reading, 2005 January 18; 1 (Box 3, Item barcode 39002099364896)
  - Toscano, Rodrigo and Elizabeth Willis. Poetry reading, 2005 February 22 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Yale Student Poets. Poetry reading, 2005 April 12 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    Students: Austin Allen, Diane Bilyak, Paula Brady, Gabriele Hayden, Caitlin Mitchell, Alex Nemser, Katherine Tsai, Ivy Wang, Ivanna Yi
  - Joseph, Allison. Poetry reading, 2005 April 20 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Alexie, Sherman. Reading, 2005 September 16 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - DeGuy, Michel. Poetry reading, 2005 October 3 (Box 1, Folder 21a)
  - Gizzi, Peter. Poetry reading, master copy, 2005 October 26; 1 (Box 3, Item barcode 39002099364904)
  - Dawes, Kwame and Goodison, Lorna and Nelson, Marilyn. Poetry reading, 2005 November 9; 1 (Box 3, Item barcode 39002099364912)
  - Swensen, Cole. Poetry reading, 2005 November 10; 1 (Box 3, Item barcode 39002099364920)
  - Rankine, Claudia. Poetry reading, 2005 November 16; 1 (Box 3, Item barcode 39002099364938)
  - Earling, Debra Magpie. Reading, 2006 January 25; 1 (Box 5, Item barcode 39002099364987)
  - Alexander, Elizabeth and Matthea Harvey. Poetry reading, 2006 February 22; 1 (Box 5, Item barcode 39002099364995)
  - Yale Student Poets. Poetry reading, Tape I, 2007 April 25; 1 (Box 6, Item barcode 39002099365018)
    Students: Georgina Banita, Mary Daniel, Rebecca Dinerstein, Adam Eaker, David Gorin, David Griswold, Erich Matthes, Chiara Scully, Jennifer Sorkin, Samantha Tonini
  - Ashbery, John. Poetry reading, Battell, 2006 September 20; 1 (Box 5, Item barcode 39002099364946)
  - Howe, Fanny. Poetry reading, 2006 October 18; 1 (Box 5, Item barcode 39002099364979)
  - Trethewey, Natasha. Poetry reading, 2006 November 8; 1 (Box 5, Item barcode 39002099364961)
  - Hayes, Terrance and Major Jackson. Poetry reading, 2007 February 1; 1 (Box 6, Item barcode 39002099365034)
  - Padgett, Ron. Poetry reading, 2007 April 11; 1 (Box 6, Item barcode 39002099365026)
  - Yale Student Poets. Poetry reading, 2007 April 26; 1 (Box 5, Item barcode 39002099364953)
    Students: Austin Allen, Paula Brady, Emily Kopley, Caitlin Mitchell, Alexander Nemser, Jennifer Sorkin, Ivy Y. Wang, Ivanna Yi
  - Komunyakaa, Yusef. Poetry reading, 2007 September 20 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Bernstein, Charles. Poetry reading, 2007 October 16 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Bök, Christian. Poetry reading, 2007 November 1 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Foust, Graham and Elizabeth Robinson. Poetry reading, 2007 November 15 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Bidart, Frank. Poetry reading, 2007 November 27 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Hall, Donald. Poetry reading, 2008 February 6 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Amad Jamal Johnson, Douglas Kearney, and Evie Shockly. Poetry reading, 2008 October 28 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Trethway, Natasha. Poetry reading, 2009 November 18 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Yale Student Poets. Poetry reading, 2010 April 7 (Box 1, Folder 51)
    Students: Alice Baumgartner, Edgar Garcia, Amy Lee, Laura Marris, Caitlin Mitchell, Rosanna Oh, Sarah Stone, Justin Sider, Katy Waldman, Eric Ward, Jeffrey Zuckerman.
  - Valentine, Jean. Poetry reading, 2010 September 29 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Yale Student Poets. Poetry reading, 2011 April 20 (Box 1, Folder 53)
    Students: Ilan Ben-Meir, Elisa Gonzalez, Alice Hodgkins, Laurel Hunt, Casey Blue James, Kate Lund, Noah Warren, Cooper Wilhelm, Jesse Williams, Hannah Zeavin
- Other Material, 2002-2006; Series II; 0.42; (1 box)
  Series II. Other Material is arranged chronologically.
  - Yale, A Place for Poetry. The Bollingen Prize for Poetry at Yale, 1949-2002, printed material (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Yale, A Place for Poetry. The Bollingen Prize for Poetry at Yale, 1949-2002, VHS recording, 2002 September 19; 1 (Box 2, Item barcode 39002099365000)
  - Yale, A Place for Poetry. The Bollingen Prize for Poetry at Yale, 1949-2002, VHS recording, 2002 September 9; 2 (Box 2)
    These videocassettes are duplicates and have not been digitized.
  - Yale College Poets and Yale Student Poets, pamphlets and announcements, 2002-2006 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Intimate Circles: American Women in the Arts, announcement, 2003 July (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Intimate Circles: American Women in the Arts / Extravagant Crwod: Carl Van Vechten's Portraits of Women, broadside, 2003 July
  - Mina, Maxine, Marianne... and More: new settings by Yale composers of texts by women whose papers are held in the Beinecke Library: H.D., Maxine Kumin, Mina Loy, Marianne Moore, and Gertrude Stein, program, 2003 October 1 (Box 2, Folder 32a)
  - Fliers for readings, [2003-2006], undated (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Rita Dove reading, broadside, [2004] November 30
  - Sherman Alexie reading, broadside, 2005 September 16
- Oversize, 2; (1 box)
  - Broadside for Intimate Circles / Extravagant Crowds, 2003 July (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - Broadsides for YCAL readings, [2004]-2005 (Box 4, Folder 35)
- Restricted Fragile, 0.84; (2 boxes)
  Restricted fragile material. Digital Reference copies available. Consult Access Services for further information.
  - Box 1, folder 21 (Box 3, Folder +)
  - Box 1, folder 22 (Box 3, Folder +)
  - Box 1, folder 23 (Box 3, Folder +)
  - Box 1, folder 24 (Box 3, Folder +)
  - Box 1, folder 25 (Box 5, Folder +)
  - Box 1, folder 26 (Box 5, Folder +)
  - Box 1, folder 27 (Box 5, Folder +)
  - Box 1, folder 37 (Box 5, Folder +)
  - Box 1, folder 38 (Box 5, Folder +)
  - Box 1, folder 39 (Box 5, Folder +)
  - Box 1, folder 40 (Box 6, Folder +)
  - Box 1, folder 41 (Box 6, Folder +)
  - Box 1, folder 42 (Box 6, Folder +)
  - Box 1, folder 36 (Box 6, Folder +)
  - Box 1, folder 43 (Box 6, Folder +)
  - Box 1, folder 45 (Box 6, Folder +)
  - Box 1, folder 46 (Box 6, Folder +)
  - Box 1, folder 47 (Box 6, Folder +)
  - Box 1, folder 48 (Box 6, Folder +)